This instructional video is recorded in Finnish language.
For English translation, please turn on subtitles.
Also in Swedish.
Our subject is the proper distribution of God's Word from the perspective of the Law and the Gospel.
This is useful both if you preach and share the Word yourself,
or wish to evaluate all teachers based on how they preach,
For the Bible invites us to test everything and keep that what is good.
So even if you are a simple layman listening on a church bench,
even then it will be of great benefit if you comprehend how the Bible is explained so that it will be understood correctly.
Let's start with God's Law.
“And if any man think that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know.” (1 Cor 8:2)
This is mostly about that
when the Word of God is read, preached, and shared,
there are two kinds of material in it.
There's God's Law and there's God's Gospel.
The Law is always demanding the perfect.
That which no man is able to fulfill.
Now the problem arises, should a man think that the Law is an easy thing.
Then he hasn't understood it yet. That is what God's Law demands.
And if a man doesn't know it, then he doesn't probably know the Gospel so well either.
Because if a man thinks to be by himself in some way eligible in front of God,
then he doesn't need the Gospel for anything either.
He doesn't need Christ absolutely for anything.
Those who preach with with such inadequate knowledge and skills
however successful may they be in the sight of men
they don't know anything.
At least not yet.
Lutherans have long had a clear view of what the Bible contains
and how the Bible should be preached.
There're two kinds of material. As Jesus says in Matthew 13:
“Then said he unto them, Therefore every scribe which is instructed unto the kingdom of heaven is like unto a man that is an householder, which bringeth forth out of his treasure things new and old.” (Matthew 13:52)
Old: that's the Law.
Which tells us what is the perfect will of God demanding such sanctity which a man cannot achieve.
And then the new, which gives that what the Law demands.
And that new doesn't demand in itself anything at all whatsoever.
Now when we deal the texts of the Bible, when those are correctly preached,
so inevitably there will be situations similar to those in the second chapter of Acts.
When it is said of a crowd:
“Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their heart, and said unto Peter and to the rest of the apostles, Men and brethren, what shall we do?” (Acts 2:37)
Man hears that God demands.
The natural reaction to that is that now I have to do something.
That I should accomplish something and hence be worthy of God.
Such a sting in the heart, or in other words, that the word terrifies when it reveals the person’s true state.
That's the first part of repentance. That's an important part because
if man does not know what he owes before God, then what does any answer for it matter either?
The psalmist is well acquainted with the requirements of God's law.
“And enter not into judgment with thy servant: for in thy sight shall no man living be justified.” (Psalms 143:2)
You can be righteous in front of people
and blameless before men. And you should be that.
But before God it is not enough.
Conscience waking up to know that thing is not common today.
It is unfortunately rare.
And so when that part of the Law perishes and disappears, so dilutes also the Gospel into meaninglessness.
The Romans say it very clearly:
“For all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God;” (Romans 3:23)
So when we talk about the Law,
we aren't talking of lifestyle choices that you can influence yourself.
Not so much talk about whether you are kind to your neighbors.
That kind of good things can even the unbelievers do. At least superficially.
But if we go to the judgment seat of God,
no one will not last when dealt according to the Law.
Therefore, it is perhaps more understandable when Jesus speaks of the Last Judgment
why the righteous wonder when we have done good, when we have seen you naked and clothed you.
Because they know their own state well.
And then on the other hand those who are going to perish
they wonder exactly the same thing: when have we seen it?
Because they think that they have merited in front of God quite satisfactorily so far.
But that's not how it goes.
But all people, everyone by nature,
Because everyone has sinned.
And all are without the glory of God.
The Romans explain further:
“Moreover the law entered, that the offence might abound. But where sin abounded, grace did much more abound:” (Romans 5:20)
The second use of God's Law is very clearly visible in here.
The first use is lifestyle choices and the fact that God wants to protect life.
That bad people don't do bad things,
to that end, there is a sword-bearing precedent that keeps such people in check.
But the second use of the Law after which the Gospel is fit to be preached
the second use of Law is in here.
The purpose of the Law is not to provoke opposition and anger, although it does also that.
But its real function is to grow into Christ.
So that grace becomes even greater.
Abundant.
And it becomes precisely that through a clear and great sense of guilt.
“But I say unto you, That every idle word that men shall speak, they shall give account thereof in the day of judgment.” (Matthew 12:36)
In it, the Law is very clearly visible.
Have you ever spoken useless idle words?
Have you heard sermons where the interpretation strays so far from the text that it really contains useless words?
Such a teacher makes an account of every useless word on the day of judgment.
Now it is a whole different matter when preachers are evaluated,
it is true that all men by themselves are without the glory of God
in some sense it is an impossible task to preach well and correctly
for there is no one in this world who masters his tongue perfectly.
Those useless words will surely come, even to preachers.
But will there be a lot of them? And is that the rule more than the exception?
This is a useful thing when evaluating teachers.
Do they talk about what the Bible says?
And do they explain the Bible in a way so
that it serves the purpose of the Bible, what that particular text speaks of at any given time?
Even if the sermon was eloquently magnificent,
it is of no use if it drifted from the text and mislead its listeners.
This verse is also a great example of the unconditionality of God's Law:
every idle word that men shall speak, they shall give account thereof in the day of judgment.
What do you think will happen to you that day if you don’t have Christ?
The Law requires something that a person cannot keep.
And it aims to
that well and correctly preached Word
blocks up all opponents' mouths.
No one can say even the first word against it.
It is a pity that there are so few such preachers.
But it is still possible.
“For the word of God is quick, and powerful, and sharper than any twoedged sword, piercing even to the dividing asunder of soul and spirit, and of the joints and marrow, and is a discerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart. Neither is there any creature that is not manifest in his sight: but all things are naked and opened unto the eyes of him with whom we have to do.” (Hebrews 4:12–13)
In a way, it’s easy to hear from this that the Law is surprisingly easy to preach.
If you try at all, it is enough to read the Bible text and ask: What does this text require?
That's the Law simplified.
Of course, a good preacher then reads from the same text: Who will fulfill that Law?
And is there also something in this text that only gives to man?
As for the Law it goes like this: even the most secret thoughts of the heart are judged by the Word of God.
You might try to pretend almost anything to other people,
you might even try to lie to yourself,
but to God you can not.
For the Word of God is effective by itself.
In a way that you cannot negotiate with it.
It grabs you by the neck and carries you wherever it wants.
At that point, the person himself maybe realizes that it was not quite so as he thought.
And when a person's own beliefs are shed,
so begins the Gospel to do as well.
It is not good for man before the Law has taken its effect.
And therefore, when dealing with any Bible text,
it is useful to consider that if you want someone to understand this matter,
then perhaps you should first say a few words about what God requires in that particular text.
Then there are also texts in which the Law and the Gospel are present at the same time.
For example, this verse of the first chapter of Romans:
for there is no gospel for one who despises the cross of Christ.
It has mere judgment and demand.
But then again, for all repentant sinners, there is pure grace and peace in it, at the same time.
How such a text is dividable may require a little experience.
But the idea is probably very easy to understand,
that in such Bible passages it is not worth committing violence to the interpretation that the text itself gives.
It is not to be forced in either direction, but rather to let it effect as it is.
And so this verse, Paul writes:
“For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God unto salvation to every one that believeth; to the Jew first, and also to the Greek.” (Romans 1:16)
The Gospel is there when Jesus says on the cross, "It is finished."
All that what the Law requires: Christ has lived a perfect life,
which God counts for the merit of every man whom He adopts as His own child.
John writes:
“When Jesus therefore had received the vinegar, he said, It is finished: and he bowed his head, and gave up his spirit.” (John 19:30)
The Gospel is the gospel of the cross.
If the proclamation of the gospel is missing Easter,
the crucifixion and resurrection of Christ,
so then one may begin to wonder whether this is the Gospel that is in the Bible.
Or is this another gospel?
As John the Baptist says:
“Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the sin of the world.” (John 1:29b)
Preaching the Gospel is in a way much harder than preaching the Law.
More or less every person understands what God’s Law is and what it requires.
Even if a person explains it away for themselves or has a hardened heart, or leads a non-Christian life.
But preaching the Gospel is more difficult, because
when the crowd felt the sting in their hearts:
That's the first part of repentance - frightening because of sins.
It is familiar to all people.
Every once in a while, at least for normal people, there are times when one goes to himself and understands their wrong actions and that things aren’t going well.
And when the Law of God accompanies that, the thought of a natural man is that now I must amend for it.
But John the Baptist says: “Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the sin of the world.”
Those works, all the doing what the Law demands from a terrified conscience,
is primarily in it and only in it.
That it's Christ who takes away all that causes conscience to tremble before God.
So it is not considered a fault by the final judgment.
And here it comes to
that not all people understand the Gospel.
And even if they somehow understood, it’s an insane idea for them.
And here is a verse that is sweet to all Christians,
and quite awful to others should they understand it.
They may not understand because by the grace of God,
so that they don't have to live the rest of their lives in anticipation of a horrendous judgment.
In the first chapter of the first Epistle to the Corinthians, Paul writes:
“For the preaching of the cross is to them that perish foolishness; but unto us which are saved it is the power of God.” (1 Cor. 1:18)
God has chosen a way to save people which humiliates the proud.
Those who imagine they know something, even though they don’t know anything yet.
Now when you consider how to explain the word of the Bible,
after all of the above, it's a pretty good guideline
that the word of the Bible should be kept as pure as it is.
If any question leads to difficult follow-up questions, then
if the preacher recognizes that if he would preach on that subject he will not able to answer follow-up questions from the parishioners
and wouldn't be able to deliver pastoral care properly as he should as the servant of Christ,
so that’s a pretty good sign that — well then, no preacher is perfect
and if there is such a clear subject area that leads to impossible questions then
then it is wisdom to keep the word as it is.
Peter writes:
“As newborn babes, desire the sincere milk of the word, that ye may grow thereby:” (1 Peter 2:2)
There may very well be texts that, although they are the word of God and drive Christ, and if properly understood, it is a sweet text,
but it may be because of your own skills
it is worth sticking to what you clearly understand,
stay in what is the unadulterated Word,
and watch out for that
that the preacher would drift into a situation
— it's the worst mistake you can make —
to the situation where he imagines he is preaching the Gospel
but preaches instead works.
A worse mistake one cannot make.
John the Baptist gives instruction to all preachers.
And when you evaluate all the teachers, you can weigh how well it comes to fruition
in the preachings of that teacher.
He says: “He must increase,” that is Christ.
“but I must decrease.” (John 3:30)
There is hardly any better guidance
what a preacher can keep in the church sacristy on the wall.
The Gospel, the Gospel is inherently foreign to man.
It is something that a natural person cannot think of.
Unless God reveals it Himself, the Gospel will remain completely foreign and superficial to man.
And because of that, for the same reason.
Because even in every preacher there is an old man who willingly opposes all that is good for God.
That is why preaching the Gospel is so much more difficult than preaching the Law.
Preaching the law properly is easy.
But if you are a preacher.
Try it at the clock.
Preach half the time first the Law.
And then spend the same time actually preaching the Gospel.
Then you will realize how difficult it actually is to preach the Gospel.
Words run out quickly.
And explaining it, it just isn’t easy.
In addition, of course, there are the things that if
if the Gospel should not really be preached — there are situations where
that one should really only preach the Law, or almost the Law alone
maybe one should prefer the latter
because no preacher will want to feel it
that someone went to the church bench to listen to his last sermon and it contained nothing but the law and after that he died without Christ.
But as you may see here, too
taking away false beliefs with the help of God’s Word
it is much much easier than proclaiming the Gospel so that you too may believe in it.
And for that matter
everyone needs God’s grace and help.
That is partly also the reason why recent converts
are advised not to become shepherds.
Because man naturally knows the things that the Law requires,
but drifting into a situation where the preacher imagines he is preaching well
while he actually divides the word of the Bible incorrectly
therefore, it is far better for the pastor of the church when he is called to that office
so that he has truly seen the life of a Christian,
heard the Gospel.
Maybe you could use that kind of language that
that if you have just recently been cleansed in the rain of God's Word,
then it pays to stay in the rainfall for a much longer time so that you thoroughly become clean.
Because then the words which will arise from your heart are probably more in harmony with what the Gospel says,
when you know the Gospel better.
1 John 2:2
verse is a very strong and powerful Gospel
It is objectively present that the whole world is reconciled.
And then subjectively the fact that also our sins have been atoned for.
And that is exactly what the Gospel is all about.
The Gospel gives everything it promises,
and does not require anything. And that is the second part of repentance.
Now if you think an occasional friend coming to the church to listen.
How to divide Word so that he hears the word correctly, if it is possible for the preacher.
Yes, then both parts of repentance must be present.
The fact that God's Law terrifies conscience.
And that the Gospel gives and bestows all that the Law requires.
All the treasures of salvation.
In it immediately, without demanding anything.
As John writes, the Gospel at its best:
“And he is the propitiation for our sins: and not for ours only, but also for the sins of the whole world.” (1 John 2:2)
In that work, the Atonement, and the righteousness of Christ, is where every preacher remain themselves as well.
And every Christian
considers it the most important thing in this world.
Remain in the peace of the Lord.
Scripture taken from the Holy Bible, King James Version.